hello and welcome everyone this is
active inference math stream 9.1 on
March 5th
2024 we're here with Jonathan gorard and
we'll be discussing a variety of topics
yet to be determined or are they so
thank you for joining and to you for any
introduction and we'll really look
forward to everyone's comments and
questions so thanks again for joining to
you
okay well yeah thanks very much Daniel
for for the the introduction and for
inviting me to be here on on active
inference it's it's uh I'm looking
forward to a very very fun discussion um
so uh I don't I mean it's I don't have
anything especially prepared to talk
about which is probably a good thing
because it means we'll we'll be able to
extend the kind of the unstructured part
of this for for as long as possible but
I think just to give a little bit of
context I I want to talk about an area
where I think some things that I've been
working on some collaborators of mine
have been working on uh that might have
some kind of intersection of Interest
with things that you know active
inference type people might might care
about right so um and in particular that
concerns the relationship between kind
of computation observation and cognition
and specifically using methods that come
from category Theory and topos theory
and some other kind of branches of of
mathematics and theoretical computer
science to understand the relationship
between uh system specifically the
computational and algorithmic complexity
of systems versus the computational
algorithmic complexity of observers of
those systems and how those things trade
off between each other so uh so just to
give a little bit of context to that I I
want to show these are just some visuals
from a a paper that I put out uh about a
year ago now um and that this kind of
really defines This research program
that I've been working on for the last
year and a half in some form or another
which is looking at exactly this
trade-off uh using category theoretic
Machinery so here's a specification of a
touring machine this is just a simple
deterministic computation it's saying
you know you have a touring machine that
has this head State and this tape State
and on the next step you're going to
replace the the tape state with
something that looks like this the head
state with something that looks like
that and you're going to scroll the
touring Machine Head left or in this
case scroll it right uh Etc so this is
just a you know specification of a very
simple computation a I think this is a a
two-state two color touring machine on a
simple you know onedimensional tape it's
about a simpler computation as you could
Define so if you run that thing for some
initial condition you'll get uh an
evolution that looks like this um and so
right now this is just a purely
deterministic you know single path
Evolution uh but from this we can
construct uh we can build a mathematical
structure namely we can build a category
uh so and the rules for how we build
that category are very simple so you
know each Arrow here is some some simple
computation some application of the
touring machine transition function and
then what we can do is we can say well
anytime we have two arrows that are laid
end to end like this we can compose them
together to create a third arrow that
goes like that I I may even have a
picture yes like this so so you know we
have a computation F that takes us from
X to y a computation G that takes us
from y to Z and we can then that we we
obtain a composite computation G compose
F that takes us directly from X to Z and
we also add some some uh some additional
edges some additional arrows uh on each
state itself a sort of identity comp an
identity operation that Maps a
computational state directly to itself
and so this combined with uh some axioms
of associativity and ident
forms a category of Elementary
computations so this is a very very
simple example but what I want to try
and build up towards uh and kind of pump
your intuition for is uh a category
which I call comp which is a category
whose objects are all essentially this
the class of all data structures and
whose arrows or morphisms are the class
of all elementary computations so you
start by just applying you know all
possible computations or you know in
this case for the case of touring
machines all possible uh you know
touring machine transition functions and
then you do this closure operation where
you uh you know where where you
essentially do what I'm doing here but
you you know you you allow those
Elementary comp computations to be
composed together in arbitrary ways and
so that gives you effectively a class of
all possible programs so this category
comp contains not only all possible data
structures as objects but all possible
programs as morphisms and this is a a
very rich category with some very
interesting algebraic structure that
we'll kind of again I'm sure we'll
allude to in our subsequent discussion
um but uh in a sense when we do this
when we do this operation of taking what
mathematically we call a transitive
closure right where where where we allow
two Elementary computations to be
composed together to produce a third um
we are essentially kind of neglecting
considerations of computational
complexity right because you know um
this Arrow here might correspond to one
application of the touring machine
transition function this Arrow might
correspond to another application of the
transition function but this composite
Arrow correspond might correspond to two
applic ation of the transition function
and so somehow when when we when we
allow arrows or morphisms to be composed
in this way we're neglecting
considerations of the complexity of
operations so the question then is you
know could we imagine uh constructing a
generalization of category Theory which
takes into account computational
complexity so here's a an example of how
that would look right so here you can
see every Edge every morphism has been
tagged with certain computational
complexity information in particular
it's been tagged with a number
specifying what is the minimum number of
applications of my transition function
what's the minimum number of Elementary
computations that I need in order to
evolve from this data structure to this
data structure so here to go from here
to here it's just one to go from here to
here it's one to go to from here to here
it's one Etc uh but to go to from here
to here directly it would be three uh to
go from here to here directly it would
be two um and you know just for
convention we we say that the identity
uh the the identity computation the
trivial computation always has
complexity zero um and then this this
so this is a again a fairly simple
mathematical structure and you can uh
you can construct this uh again using
purely category theoretic technology um
by by building a a particular funter
from uh a from the category of
computations and from the category of
data structures and computations to a
what's called a discrete cobordism
category and again we might discuss that
later on if if if people are interested
but let me not get too bogged down into
the technical details of how we do that
but once you've got this it gives us
immediately a very nice way of
characterizing phenomenal like
computational
irreducibility so uh there is this idea
that um has existed in some form or
another since the very early days of
theoretical computer science since the
days of you know girdle and touring and
post and and church and so on uh but was
given this term computational
irreducibility by by Steven wlr uh with
with the where the idea is essentially
that uh you just you know intuitively
you describe a computation as being
irreducible or you know the result of
the computation as being irreducibly
complex if uh it's not possible to
shortcut it in any way right so where
you know it takes that computation takes
a certain number of steps and there does
not exist a shorter computation that
would give you the same answer in less
time um and one of the nice features of
thinking about computations and their
complexity algebraically like this is
that it gives you a purely algebraic
characterization of irreducibility in
particular what it says is that
irreducible computations are ones for
which uh the computational complexity
acts additive purely additively under
composition so if it if it's the case
that if we compose say two uh um
computations of complexity one together
uh if the if the resulting composite
takes you know has complexity two then
it's an irreducible computation if it
has complexity less than two like one
then that means that we could have we
could have jumped directly from the
input to the output without having to
pass through the two Elementary
computations that made it up so that
would be an example of a reducible
computation so reducible computations
are ones whose complexities compose Sub
additively in this category theoretic
sense
um and okay so here's an here's a an
illustration of uh showing what what
intermediate computational States you
had to go through in order to get from
one data structure to another data
structure so to go from here to here you
had to go through steps one to two to go
from here to here you had to go through
steps one two and uh one two three and
four Etc so you can build up a kind of
complete algebra of complexity this way
which has some some nice properties
which again I I I can talk about but I'm
I'm let me not get too down in
mathematical details right now um but
here's the thing I really want to talk
about which is what happens when you do
when you go to to uh to multi-way
systems what happens when you go to
non-deterministic computations so now
imagine having instead of just a touring
machine with a single rule a single um
transition function that just evolves
deterministically with a single thread
of time now imagine having a turning
machine that has say two transition
functions like this one and this one and
so at any given point it can apply one
of the two um and so now our Evolution
instead of just being a single path
becomes this kind of branching structure
which if if we didn't have any merging
would be a tree uh but because we are
merging equivalent States it's actually
just a kind of more General uh directed
graph um and so so it looks like this
and this we we we call a multi-way
system and so we can build a category
out of these multi-way systems as well
we can build a category in exact using
exactly the same rules so again we we do
this transitive closure operation so we
we add an edge for every for every um uh
every possible composition of these
Elementary computations and an identity
Edge that Maps every data structure to
itself um but it turns out this category
has even more structure than the single
way uh uh system that that we showed
previously because now it's possible to
compose computations not just um
sequentially in time using ordinary
composition but it's possible to compose
them in parallel uh across what is
sometimes referred to as branchial space
so so essentially you're you're saying
instead of you know the the the the
ordinary morphism composition that I
showed previously is essentially saying
you know I apply this comput I apply
this Elementary computation then this
Elementary computation sequentially um
whereas this uh parallel composition is
saying I apply this computation and this
computation in parallel to the same data
structure and so that so that parallel
operation is what causes these branches
right effectively when you when you have
two uh you know two threads of time that
are branching from the same state like
here uh what that's that's arising
because we have chosen to apply this
Elementary computation and this
Elementary computation together in
parallel rather than than sequentialized
in
time um and so this this and so here you
can see this this parallelization
indicated using what's referred to as a
branchial decomposition which is just a
kind of a visual way of decomposing
what's what's going on between these
different threads of time and again
there's a purely algebraic
characterization of what's going on here
which is that uh what we've done is
we've taken our our simple category that
we started with and we've equipped it
with a tensor product structure and so
it's become what we fancy call a
monoidal category or actually symmetric
monoidal category so the tensor so we we
now have these two operations we have
sequential sequential composition in
time and we have this tensor product
operation which is a parallel
composition in branchial
space um and just like we can have just
like before we where we equipped uh our
our edges our morphisms with certain
computational complexity information uh
we can do the same thing and we
described how those complexities
composed sequentially in time we can do
the same thing and describe how the
complexities compos parallel as one
composes morphisms in branchial space
and so this allows one in by exactly the
same token to quantify multic
computational irreducibility rather than
just computational irreducibility so now
multic computational irreducibility
becomes a measure of how additive or
subadditive your time complexities are
when you compose them in parallel
through the tensor product rather than
just in sequence through standard
morphism
composition um okay but I promise I I I
am so here's an analogous diagram to the
one I showed before showing all the kind
of intermediate Med steps uh that that
are being uh that that are being applied
when one composes uh computation when
one constructs computations or indeed
multi computations by composing
Elementary computations both
sequentially in time and in parallel in
in branchial space now but I promise I I
I am the the point that I'm trying to
get to is that it turns out that in
addition to just being a useful way to
think about computational complexity
Theory and to formulate complexity
classes like you know polinomial time or
nondeterministic polinomial time Etc it
turns out this is also an interesting
way to think about the role of
observation in uh in in sort of
computational models of reality because
so and here's where I'm going to get a
little bit philosophical and I don't
have I don't immediately have a slide
that or a graphic that I can show to
illustrate this point but so um when we
think about modeling a system
computationally uh one has to bear in
mind that there are really two
computations going on right there's
there's the computation that the system
is itself performing and then there's
the computation that the Observer the
person who is measuring measuring that
system and concluding things from it uh
that there's the computation that they
that they are performing and somehow you
know so when we construct models of
reality or when we construct models of
systems you know and we want to describe
kind of at a meta level what we're doing
in computational terms there's our own
computation that you know that's going
on inside our own internal
representation of the world and then
there's presumably some external
computation that's going on outside and
then when we make observations and when
we make measurements when we construct
theoretical models um what we're doing
is we're somehow constructing some kind
of encoding function that allows us to
take a a concrete physical state of the
system we're observing and encode it as
some abstract state of the internal
model that we have of what's going on
and that's all very well but then one
but then now we we don't just have one
computation to care about we have three
right we've got the computation of the
system computation of the Observer and
the computation this this encoding
function computation that's responsible
for their for their you know the the
interface between their internal model
of the world and the external reality
and the computational complexities of
these computations into play in an
extremely interesting way and so the you
know part of the reason for trying to
develop this algebraic semantics for
thinking about computational complexity
and multic computational complexity was
to try to give one a systematic way to
reason about exactly this three-way
interplay between systems observers and
encoding functions and so in particular
when when we make when when an observer
makes a model of the world one thing
that they're doing is that they are you
know for any for any model isn't just
you know a complete description of
reality there's a certain amount of
course graining right there's a certain
amount of uh um taking a bunch of states
that in the system itself are
distinguished but in the internal model
are treated as the same they're kind of
you know they're cast in the same bucket
so in some sense you know how coarse a
model is is a measure of how much the
encoding function fails to be subjective
right and and so so again there's
there's a kind of algebraic or c
theoretic characterization of what's
going on that that you that uh that you
know um the the the the fewer of your
morphisms are epimorphisms the more
course your model is you know the more
the more abstract or idealized your
model of reality is um and so then the
interesting thing is that this
characterization of multicomp putational
irreducibility irreducibility this
measure of how additive or sub additive
your complexities are as you compose
them together in parallel gives you a
measure of the relative complexity of
the evolution function that is the the
the function that evolves your
computation forwards in Time versus the
equivalence function that is the
function that declares that two
computational states two data structures
are to be treated as equivalent and that
interplay I claim is a kind of abstract
meta way of thinking about the interplay
between uh the computation of of systems
versus the computation of observers
because you know so in it say the role
of the system is to evolve forwards in
time uh whereas the role of the Observer
is to take states in the you know in the
system that are distinguished in reality
and say you know subject to my idealized
model I'm going to treat these as the
same so the so you know the system is
defining the the evolution function but
the Observer is defining this
equivalence function and so then the the
the trade-off in their complexities
becomes exactly a trade-off between how
you know what are the um uh what are the
algebraic rules that describe the
complexities as they compose
sequentially versus the algebraic rules
that describe the complexities as they
compose under this tensor product
operation um and so yeah I I've shown
this uh in particular for for for for
touring machine systems but this is a
very say this is a very general kind of
algebraic semantics you can apply it to
hypergraphs you can apply to combinators
Lambda calculus doesn't matter uh in a
sense uh there is just one category up
to isomorphism of computation of data
structures and computations and there
are simply many different ways of
parameterizing what that category is
doing through things like tring machines
or hypergraphs or whatever some you know
the the the the algebraic formalism
transcends the particular details of the
computations that one's dealing with um
and so yeah as I say what what one ends
up with is a is a I think a fairly
general formalism for thinking about the
interplay between observers and the
systems that they
observe and uh that gives one a I I
promise I'll stop monologuing in a
moment and we'll we'll try and pick pick
apart what what I'm really talking about
here but so I'll just conclude with um
you know once once one has that
algebraic semantics a whole bunch of
things which I think previously would
have been at least to me previously
seemed like kind of fundamental confus
confusions about you know how scientific
observation works and and how it
interplays with computational models
those confusions kind of become much
easier to clarify once you think about
it in this kind of more compositional
way so um to give a very simple example
um or a kind of very uh degenerous
example
um you can you know within this
algebraic semantics you can effectively
trade off the computational complexity
of the system for the computational
complexity of the Observer right so um
you you you can have um you can have
kind of in effect two degenerate cases
you could have the case where the system
itself has a completely trivial
Evolution function the system itself has
has uh you know is doing something
completely Elementary in it in in in in
how it evolves but then the Observer has
some incredibly complicated equivalence
function that makes the system look like
it's doing something really complicated
even though what it's actually doing is
something very simple um and so then you
so you could have the phenomenon where
actually kind of all of the complexity
is in the eye of the is in the eye of
the Observer you can also have the other
degenerate case where the Observer is
doing something absolutely trivial where
the you know the encoding function or
the the observer's own internal
representation is just an identity
function or something so there's no
complexity there but the system is doing
something incredibly complex it's doing
some some totally s some really
sophisticated Universal computation and
so that will also appear very complex to
that Observer and so and and you can
also have any kind of any intermediate
you know there's there's this vast
interstitial space uh between these two
extremes and so one thing that's kind of
always uh uh one sort of philosophical
problem that I've always kind of uh been
interested in ever since I was a kid
which is this this sort of um this
tension between empiricism versus
rationalism right you know the question
of uh you know on if you look back at
the history of where you know early
European philosophy or you know yeah
certainly Western you know Western post
Enlightenment philosophy you had people
like you know decart and livits and and
so on who were who or you know and in a
more sophisticated way Bishop Barkley
with subjective IM materialism who were
trying to push for this idea that oh you
know all the all the sophistication is
what's going on inside the observer's
head and you know what goes on in
reality is somehow secondary and then
you had people like you know Lo and hum
and the empiricists who is saying no no
we should try and get the Observer as
much out of the picture as possible and
we should say all the sophistication is
going on kind of in the external world
and this in one you know one nice
consequence of this is it gives one one
nice consequence of this formalism is it
gives one actually an algebraic way of
kind of par amerzing this this spectrum
from rationalism to empirism right that
that that you can you can choose the the
rationalist extreme where you know uh
you know you just have some some space
of all possible computations and and the
Observer is doing all of the work to try
to narrow down to a particular one or
you can have the kind of empiricist
extreme where you know the Observer is
is a completely Elementary system and
you know and and everything and and
everything they observe is just being
built up from a kind of bottom up uh uh
construction all you can have anything
in between and in a sense we we now have
I think the beginnings of a mathematical
theory that explain that's able to
explain how those complexities trade off
in a in a very direct way so I think
there's potentially places of of of
mutual interest there in kind of the in
in in thinking about yeah as I say
cognition observation measurement
scientific modeling and so on in
fundamentally computational terms so I
think that hopefully that will provide
some some context for for for a
discussion
um
thank you great opening there's so many
places to uh spin in and jump
through I guess I'll start with the two
things I wrote down were Unity is plural
and at minimum two and beauty is in the
eye of the beholder and the way that
these kinds of pieces of Timeless wisdom
that describe that fundamentally
relational component to observers in
systems which are not all kinds of
systems per se but those kinds of
systems those things are true for and
then the way in which along the
formalism that you described with the
system Observer
encoding three-way partition and then
the way that in free energy principle
and the particular physics that
interface gets broken out from the
agent's perspective into the incoming
sensory and the outgoing action so then
that results in the four-fold particular
partition so maybe just to kind of dwell
there there how do we
partition the from a category Theory
perspective or however the action
perception Loop or the engagement Loop
like how do we make a topology or
compare or contrast different topologies
and flows over this kind of seemingly
pervasive or Universal interface like
concept that's a fascinating question I
I so I don't have the answer and this is
maybe a place where where um both you
Daniel and and perhaps David may may
have you know useful perspectives on
this because you know I'm
I'm you know I I I read K's work a few
years back and so I have some
familiarity with the terms but I'm by
I'm by no means kind of you know an
expert on free energy principle or you
know active inference and those kinds of
things um but I think it's a very good
point that you raise and and so you know
I I should begin by just being honest
and say that you know everything I'm do
you know all that I just described is of
course an idealization and that you know
in reality you know in particular it's
an idealization which I think you you
were very right Daniel to to kind of
pick up on it's an idealization in which
we say The Observer is completely kind
of non-interacting with the world
somehow right that that that you know in
a sense that there's just input coming
in and nothing nothing coming out uh but
of course we know that's not really how
observation Works observation is
necessarily a kind of two-way process
and so what what's needed is not just
this kind of very clean algebraic
semantics that I've described here which
assumes that there's a essentially a
one-way function from the world to The
Observer but actually uh something more
like a kind of second order cybern ICS
description uh of you know what's really
going on where where where you have uh
you know first order and second order
interactions whereas exactly as you say
you can get these sort of feedback loops
from observation to action and back
again which are probably which is I mean
still an idealization but probably a
more realistic idealization for how for
how real observers and real measurement
apparatus work so um I just want to
begin by saying that I don't know right
and and you know the question of how
this formalism interplays with things
like second order cybernetics and other
areas where I know these kinds of
questions have been explored explored
that's something I I I'm very interested
to find out about you know going going
forward um but I think H okay so yeah I
so at some point may maybe you could
help me understand you know potentially
where where things might fit in with
with the with you know with the kind of
broader active active inference um
framework
um I'm not sure I necessarily have that
much more to to comment on than that um
yeah other than to say that that you
know in a sense okay so maybe you know
one one further comment is that
um because I mean you you asked
specifically about how the the kind of
compositional category theoretic
perspective might be useful um so I I
don't think category theory in itself is
going to be the complete answer I think
it will be category Theory augmented
with some other things computational
complexity probably second order
cybernetics uh and some other things
that I that I may not be aware of um but
one place where I think that that
Viewpoint is useful at least on a
philosophical level is the idea that is
the idea that comes about that that that
you really obtain by studying
mathematical structures in a category
theoretic way which is that the identity
of
something you can Define it both in
terms of its intrinsic Properties or you
can Define it in terms of you know the
stuff that you can do to it right so you
know this was really the transition that
happened in the foundations of
mathematics as a result of people like
Samuel lenberg and Saunders mlan um so
you know category theory has its origins
in this sort of slightly abstruse branch
of algebraic topology uh it was you know
initially developed by people like
Alexander gend deque and John Pier for
doing um homological algebra for you
know for reasoning about sort of the
algebraic structure of topological
spaces but then later in the I think
1960s 1970s these two American
mathematicians eidenberg and mlan
realized that it was useful not just for
thinking about topology but for thinking
about kind of mathematical structure in
general and then later on applied
category theorists started saying well
maybe it's useful for just thinking
about structure in general but the you
know the key kind of conceptual or
philosophical shift that it imposes is
you know historically thanks to the work
of people like Kantor and frer and
Russell and so on people have thought
about mathematical structures in the
foundations of mathematics as you know
in terms of set theory and the idea in
set theory is you have this you know
things like the axiim of extension that
effectively say a set is defined by
what's inside it right so in other words
you know you you you a ma a mathematical
structure obtains its identity by you
know you break it apart and you look at
what's inside
um in category Theory it's a completely
different view the view instead is you
say well no you can't look inside you
know it's a fundamental rule of category
theory that you can't look inside an
object uh you know its internal
structure if it has any is sort of out
of bounds to you and instead you you
give that object identity in terms of
how it relates to other objects of the
same type right so in other words you
know you can ask you know what what can
I do to this what what functions can I
apply to it what functions can can I
apply to something else that map into
this uh so you know if I want to Define
I don't know uh the real numbers or the
integers or something in the set theory
St you know from a set theory
perspective he would say the the you
know the the essence of the real numbers
are all the numbers that are inside that
set all the numbers that are inside R
whereas the category Theory perspective
is no the essence of the real numbers
are all the functions that you can
Define that take real numbers to some
other number system or real numbers to
themselves or that take some other
number system into the real numbers or
Etc and you know some of the deepest
results category Theory like the on
Lemma and other things are telling one
in some very precise sense that these
two perspectives are really the same at
some fundamental level that that you
know that identifying an object based on
its internal structure based on breaking
it apart and asking what's inside and
identifying an object by asking what can
I do to it and what you know what can
this object be transformed into and what
things can be transformed into this
object those give you exactly the same
information it's far from obvious that
that's true you know the nmma is a very
kind of
uh it's one of those results where you
can never quite work out if it's obvious
or if it's incredibly you know
mysterious uh but I would I tend to fall
on the side that it's incredibly
mysterious it's far from evident that
that those two perspectives would really
be the same and yet the point you're
making Daniel I think is that uh is that
in a sense our our historical ways of
thinking about scientific observation
have tended towards the set theoretic
Viewpoint the tended towards the
Viewpoint that we we understand systems
based on kind of breaking them apart
into constituent components um but it
perhaps a more realistic view is
something more like the category Theory
perspective where we say no I I I
understand a system by interacting with
it right by by by asking what can I do
to it and how does it behave as I when I
when I perform certain operations to it
and that's a fundamentally uh you know
that's a fundamentally two-way process
that involves not just passive
observation but also kind of active
participation and somehow we need to
develop a formalism that that kind of
incorporates those two elements and
maybe you know maybe it already exists
and it and it exists in this large
literature tree uh of which I'm largely
unaware that's partly why I want to be
here to to try and find out you know
what things I missed so to
speak excellent all right a few points
self-evident is far from
evident also I tend to the mysterious
which is to say saying more with less
especially for these Frameworks because
they're less opinionated so that their
space of internal semantics can be
larger and then that description that
you provided with the relationship
between the set and the C category
Theory so I kind of summarized it as set
is to essential inclusion as category is
to relational function now if our
concept of organismality or of action in
The Niche is constructive compositional
material then we are looking for like
what is in or out is the microbiome in
is the phermone and the ant colony in or
out of that thing because it's looking
for like a static material IAL answer
and then in contrast the the other side
of that coin highlights the the dynamic
like whatever it is that's
self-organizing of the tornado is the
tornado whatever it is that's
self-organizing for the ant is the ant
um and then also this like hint SL mobus
strip or something that those two in the
moment are
indistinguishable and yet systems that
we choose to Define one way or another
or keeping both open those design
decisions do make all the difference
even if for real systems as they're
observed there's indistinguishability
right right I think that's a that's a
very important point and and one which I
mean this is a it's it's always a kind
of concern I have whenever I start
thinking about you know embodied
cognition or or you know um Extended
phenotype type ideas right that that
in a s you know if what one is trying to
do here is construct a kind of
formalistic model of of observation or
of cognition or something then as a kind
of first order approximation one has to
start by somehow decomposing the world
into observers and systems but of course
that you know we know that that
decomposition is is is somehow
arbitrarily imposed right and that you
know if you take these things to their
extremes and you you know you allow
essentially everything that the that the
agent is interacting with to be consider
you know like like not just the microb
as you say but also you know tools that
they construct or environments in which
they exist and so on if you if you as
you start to consider all of that to be
a component of that organism you know of
that agent's phenotype which is a
completely reasonable thing to do then
uh and and you start to you know you
start to say okay well their cognitive
processes are not just localized to
their brain or their spinal column but
are kind of somehow extended to you know
the computers they use the paper they
write on uh the books they read Etc
again perfectly reasonable thing to do
and sort of somehow more uh more
descriptive of what's really going on
but my fear is always if you take that
too far then you know you end up
destroying the whole assumption that the
uh that the idealization was based on
which is that you can neatly decompose
you know uh the world into into into
observers and systems and so I always
get a bit nervous when when thinking
about that that it's that it's like yes
you know in a sense yeah we know this is
an approximation and we know that that
approximation is not really true but how
how you know um how much can can you
afford to to to sort of uh to loosen
your grip on that approximation before
the whole thing just kind of falls apart
I I I don't really know the answer to
that question um but I think it's an
interesting one yeah how about ask some
questions from chat and then give your
first thoughts and then we'll see maybe
where that kind of lands with further
questions or how it connect to active
inference so that sounds good oh by the
way should I keep my screen share on or
should I should I yeah we might want to
go to a figure so it's fine okay yeah
all right Quantum Bell
wrote how does this help us reason about
causality that's a fascinating question
okay so um that that's that's another
major aspect of of you know why I think
this research program is exciting
because so
um and again this is something where I'm
interested to get the kind of active
inference perspective because I know
this again it's a topic which much has
been written and and I I'm I'm largely
ignorant um but yes so one question you
could ask is uh yeah if if you have a
description of a computation like this
like uh let's go back up to the touring
machine case the the single way touring
machine case that's relatively easy to
analyze although still far from obvious
what's going on so suppose you have a
computation of this kind and you want to
ask uh what is its causal structure in
other words you know for each Edge each
time I'm applying this turing machine
transition function can I construct some
kind of graph you know some some
directed graph representation that tells
me how these events are linked together
so in the uh within the original resarch
program this this the so-call WF for
model research program that kind of
started a lot of these investigations we
were looking at this all the time right
we were looking at kind of you know
taking computations and and looking at
their causal structure and trying to you
know infer things about what was going
on about the you know the semantics of
the computation based on uh clausal
relationships and at a certain point I
started to realize and I think other
people had realized this before I did
but I'm often slow to to pick these
things up I I I I and other people
started to realize that the notion of
causality we were using was kind of
nonsense I mean it it was not completely
hopeless but it wasn't really causality
or it couldn't really be called
causality in any in any definite sense
so um what do I mean by that so first of
all it was a very technical problem so
uh if you're looking at something like a
turning machine Evolution or a
hypography writing system as we were um
then there's a very tempting and OB
apparently obvious natural definition of
causality that you could use which is to
ask you know when you split the world up
into events that take you know some part
of your data structure as input and
output you know some other part of a
data structure is output then you can
very easily ask well does the output of
one event intersect with the input of
another event so uh if if I show the
hypergraph example it's perhaps easier
to see so you have a hypography writing
rule that looks like this right so you
know you have you say if I have a piece
of hypergraph that looks like that I
replace it with another piece of
hypergraph that looks like this so at
each each time you apply an event you
can think of that event as you know
ingesting certain hyperedges and kind of
you know replacing them with others so
you can divide it up into a sort of the
the the the input hyperedges that are
being ingested versus the output
hyperedges that are being produced and
so then you can ask well do the output
did the did I use did I subsequently
ingest in some future event hyperedges
that were output in some previous event
well if the answer is yes then pretty
obviously that future event couldn't
have occurred unless the previous event
had already occurred so then you could
say well then one of those events causes
the other so in general you could say
that two you know eight event a causes
event B if it's the case that the output
uh that the the collection of of tokens
that was produced in the output of event
a has a non-zero intersection with the
collection of tokens that were ingested
as part of the input of event B and
that's is a very tempting very natural
definition of kind of causality in these
systems turns out it doesn't really work
I mean it works pretty well but there
are cases in which it fails and it fails
pretty spectacularly and uh so the kind
of canonical case where it fails
spectacularly is that you can have
events that don't actually do anything
right you can have events that just kind
of touch an edge touch a token and and
output it again unchanged but maybe you
know change the it modifies the name it
modifies the identifier um but it
doesn't actually change anything about
the structure of the hypergraph or the
touring machine state or whatever so
pretty obviously that event doesn't
matter it can't it shouldn't be causally
related to anything in the future but
because it mod because it ingested The
Edge and then didn't do anything you
know did some identity operation but
then you know produced it in the output
again it will kind of register as being
causally related to any future event
that used that edge even though it
didn't make any difference um that's
just one very obvious example there are
other cases where it became clear that
whatever this thing was whatever this
algorithm was detecting it wasn't really
causality so I tried to think about you
know what's a more sensible definition
of causality and I I I started working
on things to do with you know a slightly
kind of blockchain inspired ideas where
you say okay well rather than just
arbitrarily assigning uh you know
identifiers to these tokens uh every
time they're created what if I
recursively construct the identif of the
token based on its causal history so in
other words each token like each hyper
Edge or each state in my each um each
tape uh Square on my touring machine uh
tape I the identifier is not just some
random number that gets generated by my
algorithm but instead it's identifier is
a directed graph representation of its
complete causal history well then kind
of recursively its identifier can only
change if the causal history was updated
and so you don't end up with these kind
of spous causal relations that I
described before so that seemed like one
tempting uh way of resolving this
problem but then I realized actually
there's a much more fundamental problem
there's a pro there's a philosophical
problem with the way that we're thinking
about causality which is that it's not
really you know
so okay this is a long tangent which
I'll I'll I'll talk about a little bit
but I won't get into the complete
details unless people are interested but
I ended up I ended up talking to a bunch
of philosophers who who you know who
worked on causality and people who
worked on Parallel programming and
Quantum information the and other places
where causality was was was studied and
asked them kind of basically what what
is what what do you mean by CA what is
causality what is this thing we're
trying to to to to Define and in some
form or another all of the definitions
boiled down to you know event a causes
event B if had event a not occurred then
event B would not have occurred so in
other words you need a counterfactual
you need some possible history some
possible World in which event a didn't
happen but if you're reasoning about a
purely deterministic event system like a
touring machine that doesn't make any
sense because if you're you know if if
you have a single touring machine
transition function there is no possible
World in which that transition function
didn't fire in that particular way
because if it didn't fire in that
particular way you would not be
reasoning about that touring machine
anymore you'd be reasoning about a
different touring machine so suddenly
this you know to make sense of these
Notions of causality you need a kind of
Li nitan you know modalities view of
reality that just doesn't exist for
these deterministic computational
systems so either you need to Define
computation you need to Define causality
only at the multi-way level only at the
level where you have many computations
or possibly all computations happening
in parallel and then you can Define
causality relative to all of you know
relative between them or you were kind
of hosed right there wasn't really you
know that that seemed like the only kind
of the only get out or you need some
fundamentally new philosophical theory
of causality that I was not qualified to
produce um and so so that that's Again
part of the reason what with the part of
what motivated this General search
program which is trying to think about
this category of not just a single
computation uh and with a single
sequence of data structures because it's
clear that you can't in a
philosophically meaningful way assign
causality in that case but rather uh you
know looking at the the the algebraic
structure of the category of all
possible computations and all possible
data structures and in that situation
there is a notion of causality you can
equip that with and uh there's a nice
again a nice mathematical description in
terms of of in terms of week two
categories and so on which again I can I
can talk about if people are interested
um but but yeah so it's clear these
things are are very deeply related that
this this sort of theory of the the
category of computations and data
structures and the theory of how you
assign causality in a meaningful way uh
are very deeply related and um I'll just
mention one other thing on that topic
which is again just area which I I I
find quite exciting because it's it's an
unexpected spin out of this program
which is that so once you have a way of
consistently applying causality at a per
token level in these systems it gives
you way of vastly generalizing what
computation is um and you can in
particular you can get you can derive
something which I call uh well I'm
provisionally calling covariant
computation although it should probably
have a better name than that which is so
you know in our traditional kind of
touring Church type po you know type
models of computation computation is a
purely Fords in time operation you know
so at every point you know you have a
complete data structure and computation
is about deriving what is the next state
of that data structure so sense it's
it's it's only a forwards and time thing
you might be able to kind of reconstruct
the initial conditions based on some
subsequent data structur so you might be
able to go backwards in time but that's
essentially what you're doing but then
you could imagine okay suppose I don't
know the complete state of my data
structure I know instead I know one part
of my data structure but I know it I
know its history throughout all of time
so you could imagine say an elementary
cellular automaton or a touring machine
tape where you know nothing about the
tape but you know the state of one cell
and you know it you know throughout all
of time and then the question is what
can you infer about the rest of the
computation and it turns out that for
those kind of structured array type
systems you can infer a lot you can
actually evolve the the system not
forwards in time but sideways in space
and obtain a kind of causal Diamond that
so okay the the the the the top left top
right bottom left bottom right Corners
are are undetermined but everything
inside that diamond can be determined
just from that one row uh or that one
column that you know uh you know sort of
extended throughout time and so
uh you know and that's a fundamentally
different notion of computation so it's
a version of computation which is not
forwards in time but sideways in space
but you can also have version of
computation that are sideways in Branch
your space where where you you know uh
you know one complete State you you know
you know one branch of the multi-way
system extended throughout time and then
the question is what else can you infer
about the you know about the rest of the
multi-way system just from that one
branch and again the answer turns out to
be you can infer a lot but not
everything and so just like in the
reason I call this covariant computation
is because it's very analogous to what
happens in relativity so in relativity
once you buy into this notion of general
covariance and the notion that space and
time are kind of fundamentally the same
thing then you have to somehow relax
your traditional view of what dynamical
systems do which is you know we we
typically think of systems as evolving
you know you have a snapshot of your
inti of your data at you know localized
on a you know for a particular state of
space you know on a particular space
like hypersurface and then your laws of
physics tell you how that space like
hypersurface evolves forwards or
backwards in time but uh
in a covariant picture of physics then
you you must also allow for you know
your initial data to be defined on a
time likee hypersurface and you for you
to be able to to evolve that Tim likee
hypersurface sideways in space or
mixtures of the two and so on and so
it's clear that there's a very general a
vast generalization of ordinary
computation theory that you can def that
you can construct that's kind of physics
inspired in that sense um in which you
can have mixing of space time and kind
of multi-way directions um in a in a
completely consistent way but to to make
those things consistent you need to have
a a definite way of assigning causality
you need because you know any
computation that you do even if it
permutes the directions of space and
time and branchial space and so on must
always somehow uh preserve the causal
structure has to respect the causal
structure of of what's going on or else
it's in consistent and so uh this this
question of how you construct a
covariant theory of computation is it
turns out intimately related to uh to
the question of how you take this
category of computations and data
structures and equip it with a with a
consistent notion of causality so very
interesting question we could talk about
that at Great length but okay to follow
with a few pieces it's very related to
Professor Mike Len's notion of poly
Computing and about the necessity for a
causality concept to be created or
deployed when the question arises was
that me was that action or change due to
me um also connectivities even just in
the neuroimaging setting which is kind
of the Cradle from which active
inference and free energy principle AR
from it's really important to
distinguish the functional effective and
anatomical connectivities and that was
one of the points that Toby St Clair
Smith made in his dissertation which is
that a lot of times the basian graphs
don't convey all of the necessary and
sufficient information to make the
reproducible computation which is one of
those kind of what's missing from the
graph is what motivated a lot of the
category Theory developments in active
inference as well as some of the formal
ontological works with sumo and Dave
here and Adam peace because implementing
modal and higher order Logics is really
important if it's a possible situation
where a mind can have a perspective on a
mind and all these things like that um
then the ant Turing tape the tape is the
pheromone and then the decision space is
the nestmates
scrolling so when you had a
deterministic turing tape that was like
a movie
because the nestmate couldn't make any
choices except for internal action which
is kind of side topic but couldn't make
any choices on the tape whereas when
there's a multi-way which is basically
in active inference what we talk about
in terms of affordances and the policy
space and the temporal depth of planning
counterfactuals on action and action
conditioned World transition States like
the B Matrix all those kinds of topics
come into play because if you want to
have a causal buffer or grasp on what is
it that something that could do
otherwise does what does it cause to do
when it does or doesn't do otherwise you
need something like a deterministic
handle around what could be a
probabilistic or deterministic but at
least multi-way map of some kind of
cognitive
territory that's a very very interesting
perspective I mean so it's again I'm I'm
I'm betraying my my ignorance of active
inference Theory here but you know it
sounds almost like so these these
um when you have this kind of interplay
between I don't know the you know
between sort of EP you know epistemic
versus uh pragmatic this you know there
there sort of two aspects of of um of of
you know of how how this kind of
speculative part of cognition Works um I
this is something which I I've thought
about I mean I I thought about in a
completely different context in relation
to things like Quantum information
Theory but I I wonder if it's I wonder
if there's a a potential overlap there
between
so there are certain situations when
thinking about these kinds of systems
purely abstractly where you kind of need
two different Notions of causality you
need a kind of speculative notion that
can be that's Dynamic that can be
Rewritten and then you need a kind of
definite notion that's that's immutable
right and so you know a classic example
of this is you know say for some
something like Quantum information
Theory right so you can have
superpositions of causal orders you can
have Quantum switches you can have uh
you know you can have causal structure
that exists in uh in in in in
superpositions of different kind of
directed graph States but then once you
apply her Mission operator once you
apply a measurement the causal structure
is definite because then everything is
relativistic and and you have covariance
and you have similar things as I
understand with with um with uh with
distributed computing with parallel
Computing where you you you potentially
allow for speculative execution for
certain number of steps where you're
kind of treeing out this multi-way
system and you have a superposition or
you know at least a collection of
possible causal histories but then
eventually you have to choose an actual
operation to do and then the causal
history you know you have this big block
that gets laid down and you know and and
then the causal history is is is somehow
definite and I I wonder if there's a
there's a way of thinking about um uh
sort of yeah you know um
speculative execution of agents and the
interrelation between that speculative
execution and you know and agent actions
in terms of again this interplay between
you know between two different causal
structures between a dynamic one versus
an immutable one yeah well one funny way
to think about that is like a single
agent that has this counterfactual
contemplative ability could be in the
center Place foraging Arena and then
imagining with discrete um branching
paths like a chess algorithm or like a
probability distribution could be like
imagining where it could go but not all
C of things are the kind of things that
make plans of their own actions whereas
like an ant colony has nestmates on the
ground so they're actually realizing in
these finite trajectories the real
exoskeleton on the ground that plays
out ending up with those simulated
trajectories could have been simulated
or could have been probabilistically
blurred but that's kind of the
difference between like the embodiment
and like the body moving there for a
mammal for an animal and then like the
mind simulating it and then just to the
um the epistemic and pragmatic trade-off
in decision-making so let's just say
that we're in that multi-way moment
we'll just have two options two
different slices of the B variable and
the policy selection question is about
which way are you going to go which
affordance in the moment policy is
basically the affordances for the time
Horizon of planning but if it's only one
time step or just an x one then the
afford in space is just the actions that
can be taken um one way to make it so
that what happens is the likeliest thing
path of least action which is kind of
what opens up the whole physics of
cognitive systems angle in contrast to
like a reinforcement or reward learning
perspective what makes it the likeliest
thing is starting with habit so it could
just be drawn from a fixed habitual
distribution however for adaptive action
habit gets upweighted with expected free
energy which is a functional that takes
in the policy space which is summing up
to one because there a probability over
actions and then upweighting
policies according to their score on
expected free energy which is consisting
of epistemic plus pragmatic value so how
much is it going to align the
observations to be what I like to see
that's pragmatic value with a
preference what is my expected
Information Gain that's the epistemic
value so how those are parameterized
make the agent that always seeks out new
information or always goes with habit
all there's so much policy space because
the knobs are not just simple sliders or
there are multiple knobs even though
they are seemingly quite consilient and
minimal like it's hard to imagine
less yet especially when there's
richness in the environment even simple
systems can have like enormously complex
or adaptive
behaviors I'll just leave it there no I
I never really thought of the so okay
the yeah two things right so so first of
all the the the perspective of you know
thinking of an ant colony or a termite
Colony or something as being you know
akin to a mind that's you know I I was
familiar with that perspective from
people like Dan Dennett and so on but
the the the idea that the individual
ants in that colony
are in a sense enact they're kind of the
hardware enacting the speculative
execution that's a very interesting idea
it's not speculative for them well yeah
no exactly but it's sort of from the
mind's perspective I guess it's almost
like speculative execution but but it's
speculative execution that's being
actuated in the physical world um which
is which is very interesting I I I not
really thought about that before um but
then yeah okay so so so then then the
yeah the the point you're making about
connection to free energy and and and of
habit for and so on that okay so um I
wonder if so you know if if we're
thinking about uh a a you know a model
of cognition in which there are these
two different you know two two distinct
causality Notions the the immutable
versus the dynamic one um I wonder if
the
so you you gave a very very nice account
of how you know habit formation sort of
works in these in these kinds of
formalisms based on you know prior
experience of of expected you know free
energy so I I I wonder if there's a way
of describing that abstractly in terms
of something like you know you you you
perform the speculative execution step
um where you you know you're treeing out
several multi-way possibilities uh and
initially you kind of you know you you
you know nothing or you have no habits
you're just kind of you're treeing
everything out with kind of equal
waiting but then you know for each
possible path you're calculating either
an actual or an expected free energy and
then somehow you know in future
speculative executions you wait those
paths which you previously had found to
have higher free energy as higher um and
so you're you know you're more likely to
explore those and less likely to explore
ones which are you know which have that
lower expected value um it feels like
something something like that should
should fit very very nicely into an
algebraic sematics like this um which
would be interesting oh how about more
questions from the
chat okay upcycle Club writes
acknowledging the limitations of
traditional entropy in multic
computations motivates us to develop
context specific entropy metrics can you
share some insights towards such
efforts yeah uh I I can certainly try um
so so yes I
mean the first point is that you know
it's I think it was there's that famous
conversation between John Von nman and
Claude Shannon where I think Von nman
famously said that like Shannon should
call his measure entropy because no one
knows what it means right and I I I
submit that the reason no one knows what
entropy means is because it's dependent
I mean okay one of the reasons no one
knows what entropy means is because it's
dependent on exactly what we've been
talking about it's dependent on the
equivalence function of the Observer so
um it's one of these things like
um I don't know maybe this is a stupid
analogy to use but
it's sorry I'm I'm I'm going to go off
on a tangent but I promise it's sort of
relevant but so um one thing okay one
thing that always breaks my brain is
when I try and think about like
actuaries and life insurance policies
because it's one of those areas
where those models only make sense if
they're not perfect in a sense right
like so if if you had an actory who knew
exactly how long everyone was going to
live um and and and somehow that
information was kind of openly available
there would be no like life insurance
policies would be pointless it it's but
you know whereas also if you had a model
that was completely hopeless of
predicting how long people would live
they would also be hope they would you
know life insurance policies would also
be
pointless that somehow the very
existence of Actuarial science relies on
your model neither being perfect nor
being awful it it somehow has to exist
somewhere in between um and I say that's
something which I I it's one of those
topics where if I think about it for too
long it all just stops making sense and
entropy has very much that same
character right because if you if you
were lassus demon if you know if you had
perfect information about the system
that you were observing there's no
notion of entropy right it's just every
you know every you know every micro
State um so that you know so so you know
the boltzman formula gives you an
entropy value of
zero where but you know the notion of
entropy only exists once you take once
you take that that perfect knowledge of
a system and you C grain it you define
as I was describing earlier you
introduce an encoding function that is
not 100% sub subjective so that now you
are mapping certain distinct micro
States onto the same coar grained macro
State and then now you can ask okay
what's the number of micro states that
you know how Co is my cor scening what's
the number of micro States consistent
with this macro State what's the number
of different values of my domain that
gets mapped to a single point in my
codomain of my encoding function and
that's what entropy is and so it's it's
very closely I mean it is effectively a
measure of how good is my course
graining so if you had perfect knowledge
there's no entropy if you have no
knowledge there's no entropy it relies
upon having a a not completely trivial
but also not 100% you know a a a a
slightly subjective but not 100%
subjective encoding function um just
like with uh life insurance policies but
so the reason the reason I'm I'm stating
that is because so now it it kind of I
think from that perspective becomes a
little bit clearer why there are all
these different Notions of entropy and
why as the questioner was alluding to
why entropy seems to be so as a as a
concept seems to be so domain and and
system specific because every different
system every different Observer will in
principle have a different set of of of
encoding functions a different set of
equivalence functions and each one will
give rise to a different calculation of
entropy um and so one way that you can
think about this program this program to
try to uh understand the algebraic
interplay between time complexity versus
kind of equivalen in complexity or or
you know computational irbil
irreducibility versus versus multic
computational reducibility in some sense
um that is a program to try to
understand how different definitions of
entropy relate to each other in these
kinds of systems um how you know if if I
if I take one idealized Observer that
has this equivalence function and I and
I ask uh okay suppose now they
communicate with this different Observer
with a different equivalence in function
they come to different understandings of
what the entropy of the system is but
what is the relationship between their
measured entropy values there clearly is
one that depends algebraically on some
details of the of the distinction
between their respective equivalence
functions but there doesn't seem to be
any yet any general theory for for you
know for how those things are related
and you know that that's part of the
kind of um the of this of this research
program um but yeah I mean okay so uh
one thing that I will comment on uh
although this is a little bit more
speculative it's again sort of Quasi
philosophical comment but so one place
where these Notions of entropy become so
one place where the fact that you have
all these different Notions of entropy
becomes kind of interesting is in
fundamental
physics so when you start to think about
if you try to model physics and and the
universe in in these fundamentally
computational terms then uh one fairly
generic sort of conclusion that you can
reach is that gravitation general
relativity is essentially an entropic
phenomenon um I mean valind and people
have kind of talked about this in in in
in non-computational contexts too but
it's very very natural if you start to
think about space like hypersurfaces
being sort of hypergraphs then you know
in order to obtain a Continuum geometry
that's compatible with the Einstein
equations you need to have certain
ergodicity uh you know um you need to be
able to make certain ergodicity
assumptions on the rewriting which in
turn sort of implies certain lower
bounds on the entropy of the system so
somehow gravitation general relativity
is a is a coar grain Theory you obtain
in the limit as the entropy goes to
Infinity but something that's
interesting is that quantum mechanics on
the other hand is an IDE is an
idealization that you obtain in the
limit as entropy goes to zero because in
in in kind of one of these purely
computational models of physics uh the
quantum mechanical state of a system is
described in terms of its multi-way
structure it's described in terms of you
know when I have a a kind of a branching
program like this let me find one of
these like this then you know I can
divide it up into these into these sort
of um into these simultaneity surfaces
and if I associate each each state of
the program as being like the analog of
a Quantum igen State and the kind of
path weightings as being you know
analogous to the amplitudes associated
with the igen states I can quickly build
up a description of this multi-way
system in terms of the evolution of some
discrete analog of the shredding
equation and it turns out you get a
theory that is kind of equivalent that
is mathematically isomorphic to standard
quantum mechanics out of it so uh
quantum mechanics is sort of you know
inextricably bound up with with with
with the with the with the phenomenon of
the multiway system but if you take the
entropy to Infinity here then you're
effectively uh then the then the
sophistication of your of your
equivalence function becomes arbitrarily
large which means that you can describe
any essentially any pair of States as
being equivalent um and so uh it turns
out that the that actually the quantum
mechanical case corresponds to the zero
entropy limit whereas the kind of
General relativistic case corresponds to
the infinite entropy limit but there
kind of two diff two fundamentally
different Notions of entropy one of
which exists at the single way level one
of which exists at the multi-way level
and uh again the question of how these
things into play is partly why we're you
know why we're investigating this and
it's clear that that that question has
links to these quite foundational
questions in fundamental
physics the ideal Point Mass and the
ideal
distribution with it center of gravity
and all this Dave question for you from
you yes
um okay I I was can you hear yep go for
it okay good um yeah I'd like to to Veer
down to the low road during this
discussion uh maybe show business when
people are trying to explain what is
computational reduci ility or
irreducibility often you'll see a a
graph that says well now here's the the
computation our Target running along the
foxes running along and behind it
there's a team of algorithms that would
like to catch it and yeah it either does
or it doesn't outrun all of them but
some can come can seem to come pretty
close to catching it um now there's
something else people have been looking
at for a few years the mandal BR set the
mandle BR set it really is a deter not
only a deterministic computation it's a
crisp computation every set every
Point either is inside the safe Zone
it's going to sit there and it's happy
and quiet and it's color black or it
flies off to
Infinity so you could it could just be a
bunch of yes or NOS but that's not the
way people trying to calm down after a a
day of work want to look at they want to
say hey I want to see the 32 million
deep mandal BR set and I want to see it
in colors so where do you get the colors
you ask how hard did I have to work how
long did I have to grind along before I
made that decision oh this is a point
that's going to settle down and be quiet
and uninteresting or it's going to fly
off to Infinity so you P put colors in
now I just wonder would it be
interesting to anyone to fuzzify these
gorgeous
causal and multicausal graphs and just
show this is the portion where we had to
work really hard rule 35 or what we had
to go 15,000 Generations before we gave
up and said we're not going to follow
this anymore the other one oh after 30
steps I I
see that's a really interesting question
and and I mean yes so uh I mean a couple
comments on on on that I mean so one is
I mean your right in the sense that yes
the M Bret is a very clean thing to
describe I would I would say it's not I
mean it's I would argue it's actually
not a crisp computation in that sense
precisely for reasons of computational
irreducibility because as you go
arbitrarily close to the boundary of the
set you can have complex numbers that
stay that have a kind of indefinite
period of transient right there's
there's no upper bound on how long the
you know Z zn^ 2 plus C orbit can can
last before it either diverges or
converges to to to you know to to zero
um and and and that statement that you
know that there are there will be points
that can you know that can remain that
can get tied up in these orbits
indefinitely is really a computational
irreducibility statement um but yeah I
mean your your question about uh you
know could you could you construct so I
mean that that that way of coloring
points that are on the boundary of the
mandle BR set in in that way that this
the so-call Escape time algorithm right
where where you kind of where you color
them based on how many steps that I need
to do before it either converged or or
or escaped off you know above some or
you know the complex numbers modulus
exceeded some value um yeah it's an
interesting idea that you could try and
kind of construct geometrical
representations of the space of possible
computations based on a kind of Escape
time algorithm for computational
risibility yeah so I mean there are
there possible ways that you could do
that right that that you you say you
know we know we've known since the days
of touring that the halting problem for
touring machines is undecidable right
there's no finite computation that you
can do that will determine whether or
not arbitary computer program will will
terminate in finite time so you could do
a you could if you once you have a way
of kind of geometri the space of
possible computations which we which we
have now as you say um yeah you could
easily construct a kind of Escape time
algorithm where you know you have your
analog of the mandle BR set which is you
know here's all the halting computations
here are all the definitely non-h
halting computations and then there's
some boundary of very fuzzy stuff where
we kind of don't really know and we have
to do a lot of work and even then it's
only heuristic um which is which is yeah
I mean very directly analogous um and
then yeah the question becomes you know
so in in the case of the mset you know
that there there is some underlying
Theory mostly I think mostly due to like
Dadi and hubard and people uh that
allows you to kind of predict like you
know if if you have a finite filament
you can of the of the mandle Bret you
can kind of predict you know where that
where that filament is going to be based
on some complicated complex analysis
argument and you know Ian the question
is once you if you once you have a
geometrization of the space of possible
computations can you construct some
general theory like the theory you know
developed by by D and hub that tells you
things about you know the topology of
the computations where the certain
regions of the of the space are
connected whether they're compact
whether you can make pred you know
whether you can do a similar thing or
you can make predictions based on the
geometry of one par ofal set you know
where you can extrapolate to things
about the geometry of another part of
the set that's a really interesting
question um and uh yeah again it's as
with so many of these things it's it's
one of these like I I don't know the
answer but it's a good reason for
investigating you know for pursuing the
program right yeah from the Wolfram side
as well as from the active inference
side there's both the information
topology and the information geometry
side and not just in the kind of
topological deep learning but rather
looking at the topology of information
flows which has been heavily developed
in the category Theory related to
Quantum information sciences and then
the information geometries that allow us
to do like machine learning type
accelerated optimization
and gradients all these kinds of
Concepts that come into play with
geometry and we just don't get them from
topology so topology kind of sketches
the skeleton and then with the computers
that we have the information geometry is
at least on the data sets and the ways
that we have computation today that's
kind of like the quantitative numerical
versus the formal um one question is are
these all discrete State space discrete
time formalisms because in active
inference we often deal with Hybrid
models that have discrete and continuous
State spaces and the same generative
model or the same system of Interest
could be modeled with like a discrete
Time chapter 7 or a continuous Time
chapter 8 model so how does this deal
with that that's a really good question
I mean yeah so so so most of what I've
been uh looking at so far has has
consisted of um discrete time discret
space uh uh models for no particular
ularly principled reason other than um
they're easier to analyze right for the
most part because you can do explicit
computations because they're kind of
more amable to constructive analysis um
it's easier to do but the beauty of a
lot of this you know that's one of the
beauty of using beauties of using kind
of General mathematical formalism is
that once you develop it um it's often
quite easy to extend even to even to
cases that you know to extrapolate it to
cases that you didn't explicitly analyze
so um in principle this formalism works
for for you know for for for Continuum
space and Continuum time systems as well
just with some you know with some slight
modifications so rather than having say
branching and merging you instead have
you know if if you think about this
thing as now being a dynamical system
you know described on some symplectic
manifold then these kind of branching
merging operations of the multiway
system become uh effectively Divergent
and convergence oper you know
differential operators defined on the
simplec manifold and uh so you know one
place where we can start to analyze that
explicitly and which I've done a little
bit of work on but it's one of these
things which I I want to go back to very
soon um is looking at Petry Nets so
Petry Nets are interesting because they
are a discrete time discrete space
system but they admit a Continuum you
know Continuum space continuum time
description in terms of ordinary
differential equations and so on so
they're they're a nice example of a
hybrid kind of discrete event versus
Continuum event system where it's clear
that this formalism can be used and and
is somehow agnostic as to whether the
you know whether the underlying system
is discret or continuous um again
there's a broader philosophical point to
make here which is that
um
in a way one of the reasons I don't feel
embarrassed to be working primarily with
discret systems is because you know
again once you start to think about
things in terms of okay you have to not
just care about nature you also have to
care about the computations The Observer
can perform and and what it Ables to
infer um then you quickly realize that
in a sense just like whatever as you
were saying earlier Danel you know
beauty is in the eye of Beholder I think
discreetness and continu and and and and
continuity are also in the eye of of a
holder right I mean so if you
have
um if you have a you know a universe
that is fundamentally continuous that's
described by you know a Continuum lenan
manifold or something but you're
constrained so that the only experiments
you perform have computable outcomes
have discrete outcomes uh where you know
where where the countable where the the
possible number of um uh you know of
observables is always countable then in
a sense it doesn't matter right it's
it's irrelevant to you as an observer
whether you know whether the whether the
system is discrete or continuous uh
because you know the only parts of it
you can interface with and interact with
are discret and so you could have
replaced the underlying substrate with a
purely discret mathematical structure
and you wouldn't be able to tell so in
some
sense uh I yeah I don't feel too
embarrassed discreet dealing with
discret Event Systems because even if I
don't necessarily believe that nature is
discreet because I don't think that's
I'm not even sure how we would be able
to answer that um I'm reasonably
convinced that that you know the the
experiments that we can perform and the
observations that we're able to perform
are ultim computable and therefore you
know the underlying substrate might as
well be discret even if it's not sort of
in reality so to
speak yeah that's a great comment
definitely calls back to your earlier
points about like discretization being
in the eye of the beholder like in the
active inference models observations raw
data may already be discretized
depending on the situation but even if
it weren't like it were a continuous
sensory perception or modeled as such
analytically still commonly models
discretize and categorize as they move
up cognitive hierarchies and that was
like initially explored to get more of
this discreet either or decision- making
planning all those kinds of properties
um well there's many interesting angles
like I'm sure also it could be a
multiplexed language model prompt but
like what are you working on or excited
about for
2024 uh that's good question um so I've
kind of already given some hints about
you know the like this this general
research program of of of trying to
understand uh computational complexity
and algorithmic complexity and
interplays between observers and systems
through this category theoretic lens
that's a yeah that's a that's a major
thing which I started on I say about a
maybe a couple years ago I mean in some
form I was I've been working on it for a
long time but but this more recent
perspective on it is maybe a couple
years old but for various reasons over
the last year or so I've kind of put
that to rest and I've been focused on
these uh much more physics oriented
questions about discrete SpaceTime and
understanding things like you know how
do black holes work and how does
secretion work in discrete SpaceTime
which is also very important and uh and
and and very exciting but uh I've sort
of slightly been missing these more
abstract directions and so I have maybe
one or two major you know physics
related things that I need to finish off
and then I and then I really want to go
back to this to to to the greatest
extent possible and yeah I mean so one
thing is
that's quite clear is that there's uh um
there's great interplay between this
formalism and ex you know an existing
theories of computational and
algorithmic complexity so in particular
you know so uh one very basic example is
I mentioned before that you know you you
you have this kind of coherence between
these two different algebraic structures
between your the the operation of Tim
like composition versus the operation of
kind of parallel composition and these
two algebraic structures are in general
related although the precise conditions
that relate them are not clear and
that's partly what we're trying to what
we're trying to understand um but it
turns out that that uh degenerate cases
of that of that question corresponds to
unsolved problems in computational
complexity Theory so for instance the P
vers NP problem can essentially be
recast in these terms that you can
recast the pp problem is the question
about uh is the coherence between the
timelike composition of computational
complexity and the parallel composition
of computational complexity which are
what p and NP respectively are really
about are those coherence conditions the
the the strictest they can be um which
would be the case that that the P equals
NP or are they somehow more LAX which
would be the case that P does not equal
NP and so there's you know that's that's
one thing that we kind of already
investigated but it's clear that a whole
bunch of questions about you know um how
the time complexity and space complexity
trade off or how do hog of complexity
and time complexity tradeoff these these
are questions which can be recast in
this kind of more algebraic category
through lens and and and um will
hopefully give insight into this general
program of trying to understand
observers and and their relationship to
the world and those are kind of major um
well with any luck those are major
theorems that I hope we'll be able to
prove at some point in 2024 um that's
but that's sorry that's that's awesome
and it makes me think about parallel
more nestmates more CPU threads deeper
in time more sequential more planning
and more cognitive single
monolithic agent and then the kind of
question is like can anything that a
single agent Mega Matrix could do cannot
be
decomposable at space advantage or even
at space disadvantage in decomposed it
into a single time step
operation yeah that's a that's a super
important question and one that you know
uh with the possible exception of this
community not many people have asked
right I mean so uh that's something
which comes up in Quantum Computing
right so um a lot of the hype around
Quantum computation comes from these
theoretical speedups that derive from
the fact that you're able to uh you know
you're able to support these superp
positions of different you know where
you know each each state of your data
structure corresponds to a different IG
State and you're able to evolve some
super superposition of those igen States
but then at the end you have to actually
come to a definite conclusion about what
the answer is you have to perform some
measurement operation and that
measurement operation is lossy it's
often non-deterministic uh you you know
often have to repeat it mult multiple
times um and you know it's it's becoming
increasingly clear that for a large
class of operations that were previously
thought to have Quantum Advantage the
additional complexity of the measurement
step really kills any Quantum advantage
that you may have had that that you you
know you get some Advantage by doing
unitary Evolution uh but then you lose
all of it by having to do this
submission projection at the end and
that's really a story of again this
interplay between the time complexity
saving of doing a multi doing a
computation multi doing a multi
computation in parallel versus the loss
that comes from the the complexity of
the equivalence function that you need
to apply in order to get to some
definite uh conclusion about what the
you know about what happened because you
know ultimately you need to somehow
collapse that that that directed graph
into a single thread uh of time in order
to be able to have some coherent
representation of what happened and so
again understand that you know that's a
place where understanding these you know
these trade-offs will become very
important and as I say in some limit in
case that that gives some perspective on
your question Daniel right which is
which you know I agree is a very
interesting question question about you
know um in principle we know that
anything that a deterministic touring
machine can do a non-deterministic
touring machine can do and vice versa
with some speed up or slowdown um but
that statement which is a classic result
in you know in computability theory
neglects all consideration of the
equivalence function so there may be
cases where the equivalence function is
so complex that essentially the you know
the the to do state equivalence becomes
undecidable and so in that case you have
a scenario where actually you you know
you've got a multi computational system
but to to collapse it to one that's
equivalent to a single way system
requires unbounded amounts of
computational effort and so so actually
they become inequivalent even though you
know computability Theory says they
should be the same um so uh it's clear
that there's a there's a a more Rich
more subtle Theory that's underlying
here that we're just beginning to kind
of Glimpse and that I hope we'll you
know we'll be able to kind of to to
prove some new limited results about
soon once we understand it a bit
better awesome and I think definitely a
special shout out to all of our
colleagues on either like the wol from
Andor octave inference side because
we've seen few if any active inference
models phrased analytically or
computationally with the wol from
technology um from studying complexity
and other
areas it's really clear to see how
productive and Powerful the software and
the tools can be and changing and
growing every day it's really
interesting maybe someone can um if
they're listening this far in like go
for one side to the other and back or
make a wol from active inference
model or do some other kind of
combination because it's very fruitful
territory and we know that our um Elders
have already
spoken they vocate it no but really it's
so many it's so rich with connections
here between um the areas that we're all
studying and feeling like converging on
many common places to to scaffold and
jump off from
together yeah I I I I agree and um I
mean at least the I mean the kinds of
things that we were discussing here
about you know speculative execution and
and and behavior formation through free
energy principle and so on those things
should be relatively easy to implement
in the framework that's already been
developed here I mean so so you know
that that's that's just a you know
that's a question of just implementing
some kind of computation of expected
free energy and using that to you know
to to to to to wait multiway paths in
the speculative execution model um so at
least the beginnings of of that
implementation I think the the path is
is pretty clear and we will probably end
up doing at some point in the future
anyway uh as part of as part of other
research um so yeah so I agree that's
it's a very it's a very exciting kind of
um point of interface yeah well I hope
that that um we can stay in touch if you
ever want to come back for a uh
9.2 or if we want to even facilitate
some kind of working group or some
connections to really strengthen and
like include the participation of more
people in this super exciting area that
would be
amazing yeah that sounds fun let's let's
try and set thing up well Dave first
penultimate comments then Jonathan you
can have the kind of last comments
yes um I hope you do get to continue on
the wolf physics side to think about a
more General notion of what these
ultimate things are uh are they
observers or does that already Prejudice
the case of what you might find if you
call them workers or actors or you know
go back and and ask steuart Kaufman what
must a mind do to earn its way in the
world let's make this keep happening
thank you thank you Dave for suggesting
it also it was a great
suggestion Jonathan no that's I think
that's a fantastic note to end on I mean
and and that that in a sense this this
idea that we should start to move I mean
so it's okay big picture for a moment
like we're you know this formalism is
being developed the the the formalism
I've described in this in this
discussion is being developed you know
assuming a kind of purely passive
Observer idealization and that's already
been incredibly difficult right it's
clear there's a lot we don't understand
at that but of course David is right
that that that in a sense you know what
you know ultimately we want to start
transitioning to a to a participatory
Observer model where where you allow for
two-way interactions or you know higher
order interactions between observers and
systems and things that don't just go in
One Direction and yeah you know in a
sense I view a lot of what we're trying
to do with you know trying to nail down
these Notions of causality trying to
understand these interplays between
different complexity and entropy
measures as you know the necessary
groundwork for developing that
subsequent Theory right that that you
know it's clear that if we want to have
a a version of the you know of this kind
of compositional multi-way formalism
that is also compatible with things like
second order cybernetics then uh you
know at the very least we need to have a
very coherent notion for what causality
is and and and you know and a robust
algebraic description of that that's not
going to to to break or change uh and so
I think um the the the non-participatory
participatory Observer model is a useful
starting point because it's one that is
just within our grasp of uh you know of
being being kind of mathematically
tractable um and then the hope is that
the technology and the the ideas and and
the conceptual structure that we develop
for understanding that will then as I
say lay the groundwork for for for
developing something that's that's more
like what real you know active
participatory observers
do um and uh and yeah I mean I I I think
I I don't on the on the scientific side
I'm not really sure I have anything any
final comments apart from just you know
as is obvious this is a you know this is
still a story that's being that's being
developed and and yeah as Daniel alluded
to I hope that we can continue to uh to
interact and and collaborate where where
that makes sense and and yeah at the
very least I think incorporation of um
kind of these you these active inference
models Within These uh discrete time in
in the first instance discrete time uh
you know computational Frameworks uh and
allowing for things like speculative
execution and multi-way path waiting
based on um free energy estimates uh I
think that's you know that that that's a
um that's a project that's obvious
mutual interest and and and something
that I that I that I hope will happen in
the coming months thank you we just
speculatively executed AC of wolf from
referance basically s all right thank
you Jonathan thank you Dave thank you
everyone see you all next
time